Once upon a time,
كان يا ما كان
there was a place called Lesterland.
كانت هناك بلاد تسمى لسترلاند
Now Lesterland looks a lot like the United States.
تشبه لسترلاند كثيراً الولايات المتحدة
Like the United States, it has about 311 million people,
كالولايات المتحدة, تعدادها السكاني يبلغ 311 مليون نسمة تقريباً
and of that 311 million people,
ومن أصل 311 مليون شخص
it turns out 144,000 are called Lester.
يوجد 144,000 شخص يدعون لستر.
If Matt's in the audience,
إذا كان ماتس بين الحضور,
I just borrowed that, I'll return it in a second,
فقط إستعرتها وسأعيدها خلال ثواني ,
this character from your series.
هذه الشخصية الكرتونية من حلقاتك.
So 144,000 are called Lester,
إذاً 144,000 شخص يدعون لستر,
which means about .05 percent is named Lester.
ويعني ذلك 0.05 بالمائة يدعون لستر.
Now, Lesters in Lesterland have this extraordinary power.
اللستريون في لسترلاند لديهم سلطة إستثنائية,
There are two elections every election cycle in Lesterland.
في كل دورة إنتخابية يوجد نوعين من الإنتخابات في لسترلاند.
One is called the general election.
إحداهن تسمى بالإنتخابات العامة.
The other is called the Lester election.
والأخرى تسمى إنتخابات لستر.
And in the general election, it's the citizens who get to vote,
في الإنتخابات العامة, المواطنون هم من لديهم الحق في الإقتراع,
but in the Lester election, it's the Lesters who get to vote.
لكن في إنتخابات لستر فإن اللستريون هم من لديهم الحق في الإقتراع.
And here's the trick.
وهنا تكمن الحيلة.
In order to run in the general election,
ولكي تترشح للإنتخابات العامة,
you must do extremely well
عليك أن تبلي بلاءاً حسناً
in the Lester election.
في إنتخابات لستر.
You don't necessarily have to win, but you must do extremely well.
ليس بالضرورة أن تكسب، لكن عليك أن تبلي بلاء حسناً.
Now, what can we say about democracy in Lesterland?
والآن ماذا نستطيع أن نقول عن الديمقراطية في لسترلاند؟
What we can say, number one,
ما نستطيع قوله، أولاً,
as the Supreme Court said in Citizens United,
كما قالت المحكمة العليا في قضية منظمة مواطنون متحدون,
that people have the ultimate influence over elected officials,
أن للمواطنين التأثير المطلق على المسؤولين الذين يتم إنتخابهم,
because, after all, there is a general election,
لأن، على أيٍّ ، هناك إنتخابات عامة.
but only after the Lesters have had their way
لكن فقط بعد أن يقوم اللستريون بإختيار
with the candidates who wish to run in the general election.
المرشحين الراغبين في خوض الإنتخابات العامة.
And number two, obviously, this dependence upon the Lesters
ثانياً, من الواضح, أن هذا الإعتماد على اللستريين
is going to produce a subtle, understated,
سينتج إنحراف دقيق، مقَلل من قيمته
we could say camouflaged, bending
و يمكننا ان نصفه حتى بالمُموَّه
to keep the Lesters happy.
لإبقاء اللستريين سعداء.
Okay, so we have a democracy, no doubt,
حسناً; إذا, لدينا ديمقراطية ,من دون أي شك,
but it's dependent upon the Lesters
لكنها تعتمد على اللستريين
and dependent upon the people.
وتعتمد على الشعب.
It has competing dependencies,
إنها تابعة لاطراف متنافسة
we could say conflicting dependencies,
بإمكاننا أن نسميها اطراف متعارضة
depending upon who the Lesters are.
تعتمد على من هم اللستريين.
Okay. That's Lesterland.
حسنا.. هذه هي لسترلاند.
Now there are three things I want you to see now that I've described Lesterland.
الآن, هناك ثلاثة أمور أريد منكم ان ترونها بعد وصفي لِلسترلاند.
Number one, the United States is Lesterland.
أولاً, الولايات المتحدة هي لسترلاند.
The United States is Lesterland.
الولايات المتحدة هي لسترلاند.
The United States also looks like this, also has two elections,
الولايات المتحدة أيضاً تبدو كذلك; لديها نوعين من الإنتخابات.
one we called the general election,
إحداهما نسميها بالإنتخابات العامة
the second we should call the money election.
والثانية يجب أن نسميها إنتخابات المال.
In the general election, it's the citizens who get to vote,
في الإنتخابات العامة، المواطنين هم من لديهم الحق في الإقتراع;
if you're over 18, in some states if you have an ID.
إن كنت تبلغ من العمر 18 عاماً، وفي بعض الولايات إن كان لديك بطاقة هوية.
In the money election, it's the funders who get to vote,
وفي إنتخابات المال، الممولون هم من لديهم الحق في الإقتراع.
the funders who get to vote, and just like in Lesterland,
الممولون هم من يقوموا بالإقتراع. بالضبط كما هو الحال في لسترلاند ,
the trick is, to run in the general election,
الخدعة هي, من أجل خوض الإنتخابات العامة,
you must do extremely well in the money election.
عليك أن تقوم بعمل جيد للغاية في إنتخابات المال.
You don't necessarily have to win. There is Jerry Brown.
ليس بالضرورة أن تكسب. هناك جيري براون.
But you must do extremely well.
لكن عليك أن تقوم بعمل جيد للغاية.
And here's the key: There are just as few relevant funders
واليك المفتاح لذلك العمل: عدد الممولين المهمين قليل
in USA-land as there are Lesters in Lesterland.
في بلاد الولايات المتحدة كعدد اللستريين; ليسترلاند .
Now you say, really?
الآن أنت تقول ... حقاً؟
Really .05 percent?
بالفعل . 0.05 بالمائة؟
Well, here are the numbers from 2010:
وهنا الأرقام من عام 2010:
.26 percent of America
0.26 بالمائة من سكان أمريكا
gave 200 dollars or more to any federal candidate,
قدموا 200 دولار أو أكثر لأي مرشح فيدرالي;
.05 percent gave the maximum amount to any federal candidate,
0.05 بالمائة قدموا الحد الأقصى لأي مرشح فيدرالي,
.01 percent -- the one percent of the one percent --
0.01 بالمائة ... بمعنى واحد بالمائة من الواحد بالمائة
gave 10,000 dollars or more to federal candidates,
قدموا 10,000 دولار أو أكثر للمرشحين الفيدراليين.
and in this election cycle, my favorite statistic
وخلال هذه الدورة الإنتخابية، فأن الإحصائيات المفضلة لدي
is .000042 percent
هي 0.000042 باامائة
— for those of you doing the numbers, you know that's 132 Americans —
- ولأولئك الذين يعملون على الأرقام منكم تعلمون أن الرقم يساوي 123 أمريكي -
gave 60 percent of the Super PAC money spent
قاموا بتغطية 60 بالمائة من من مصاريف لجنة العمل السياسية
in the cycle we have just seen ending.
في الدورة الإنتخابية التي أنتهت مؤخراً.
So I'm just a lawyer, I look at this range of numbers,
أنا فقط محامي، وأنظر إلى مدى هذه الأرقام
and I say it's fair for me to say
و أعتقد أنه من الإنصاف أن أقول
it's .05 percent who are our relevant funders in America.
0.05 بالمائة الذين هم من الممولين المهمين في أمريكا
In this sense, the funders are our Lesters.
وفي هذا السياق فإن الممولين هم لستريونا.
Now, what can we say about this democracy in USA-land?
والآن, ماذا نستطيع أن نقول عن الديمقراطية في بلاد الولايات المتحدة؟
Well, as the Supreme Court said in Citizens United,
كما قالت المحكمة العليا في مواطنين متحدين
we could say, of course the people have the ultimate influence
بإمكاننا طبعا القول أن الشعب يمتك التأثير المطلق
over the elected officials. We have a general election,
في اختيار المسؤولين المنتخبين. لدينا إنتخابات عامة,
but only after the funders have had their way
و لكن فقط بعد أن يختار الممولين
with the candidates who wish to run in that general election.
المرشحين الذين سيخوضون تلك الإنتخابات العامة.
And number two, obviously,
ثانياً: من الواضح
this dependence upon the funders
هذا الاعتماد على الممولين,
produces a subtle, understated, camouflaged bending
ينتج إنحراف دقيق، مقَلل من قيمته و مُموَّه
to keep the funders happy.
لإبقاء الممولين سعداء.
Candidates for Congress and members of Congress
إن المرشحين للكونجرس و أعضاء الكونجرس
spend between 30 and 70 percent of their time
يقضون ما بين 30 - 70 بالمائة من وقتهم
raising money to get back to Congress
في جمع التبرعات ليعودوا إلى الكونجرس
or to get their party back into power,
أو لإعادة حزبهم إلى السلطة.
and the question we need to ask is, what does it do to them,
و السؤال الذي علينا أن نطرحه هو، ما الذي يستفيدونه من فعل ذلك;
these humans, as they spend their time
هؤلاء البشر, حين يقضوا وقتهم
behind the telephone, calling people they've never met,
خلف الهواتف، يتصلون بأناس لم يلتقوهم في حياتهم قط
but calling the tiniest slice of the one percent?
يتصلوا بذلك الجزء الصغير جداً من الواحد بالمائة؟
As anyone would, as they do this,
كأيٍّ كان،نتيجة قيامهم بهذا,
they develop a sixth sense, a constant awareness
تطورت لديهم حاسة سادسة، وعي ثابت
about how what they do might affect their ability to raise money.
,حول تأثير أفعالهم على إمكاناتهم لجمع المال.
They become, in the words of "The X-Files,"
يصبحون، بتعبير فيلم `الاكس فايلز`،
shape-shifters, as they constantly adjust their views
متحولين, نتيجة تغييرهم لمواقفهم باستمرار
in light of what they know will help them to raise money,
لإتجاهات يعلمون أن سلكها سيساعدهم على جمع أموال الممولين.
not on issues one to 10,
ليس في قضايا من 1 إلى 10،
but on issues 11 to 1,000.
ولكن في قضايا من 11 إلى 1,000.
Leslie Byrne, a Democrat from Virginia,
ليزلي بيرن، عضوة بالحزب الدمقراطي من ولاية فيرجينيا،
describes that when she went to Congress,
تحدثت عن ذهابها للكونغرس,
she was told by a colleague, "Always lean to the green."
قيل لها من قبل زميل, `` دائما إنحازي للأخضر``
Then to clarify, she went on,
ثم لتوضح أكثر، واصلت،
"He was not an environmentalist." (Laughter)
``لم يكن شخصا مناصرا لحماية البيئة`` (ضحك)
So here too we have a democracy,
إذن, هنا أيضا توجد ديمقراطية،
a democracy dependent upon the funders
ديمقراطية تعتمد على الممولين
and dependent upon the people,
وتعتمد على الشعب،
competing dependencies,
اطراف متنافسة
possibly conflicting dependencies
ربما اطراف متعارضة
depending upon who the funders are.
هذا يتوقف على من هم الممولين.
Okay, the United States is Lesterland, point number one.
حسنا، الولايات المتحدة هي ليستيرلاند، النقطة رقم واحد.
Here's point number two.
هنا النقطة رقم اثنين.
The United States is worse than Lesterland,
الولايات المتحدة أسوأ من ليستيرلاند،
worse than Lesterland because you can imagine in Lesterland
أسوأ من ليستيرلاند لأنه في ليستيرلاند, يمكنك أن تتخيل
if we Lesters got a letter from the government that said,
إذا نحن اللستريين حصلنا على برقية من الحكومة تقول,
"Hey, you get to pick who gets to run in the general election,"
"مهلا، عليك اختيار من سيخوض الانتخابات العامة،"
we would think maybe of a kind of aristocracy of Lesters.
لفكرنا ربما بنوع ارستقراطي من اللستريين
You know, there are Lesters from every part of social society.
كما تعلمون، هناك لستريين من كل جزء من المجتمع .
There are rich Lesters, poor Lesters, black Lesters, white Lesters,
هنالك لستريين أغنياء، لستريين فقراء، لستريين سود، ليستريين بيض
not many women Lesters, but put that to the side for one second.
لا يوجد العديد من لستريين نساء ، لكن اترك ذلك الموضوع جانبا لوهلة.
We have Lesters from everywhere. We could think,
يوجد لستريين من كل مكان. يمكننا أن نسأل انفسنا,
"What could we do to make Lesterland better?"
"ما الذي يمكننا أن نفعله لجعل ليستيرلاند أفضل؟"
It's at least possible the Lesters would act for the good of Lesterland.
على الأقل من الممكن للستريين ان يعملوا شيئا مفيدا لليسترلاند
But in our land, in this land, in USA-land,
ولكن في بلادنا، في هذه البلاد، في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية،
there are certainly some sweet Lesters out there,
يوجد بالتأكيد بعض اللستريين اللطفاء,
many of them in this room here today,
العديد منهم في هذه الغرفة هنا اليوم،
but the vast majority of Lesters act for the Lesters,
لكن الغالبية العظمى من اللستريين تعمل من أجل اللستريين
because the shifting coalitions that are comprising the .05 percent
لأن التحالفات المتغيرة التي تشكل ال 0.5 من المائة
are not comprising it for the public interest.
لا تعمل من اجل الصالح العام.
It's for their private interest. In this sense, the USA is worse than Lesterland.
بل لمصلحتهم الخاصة. من خلال ما سبق، فإن الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية أسوأ من ليستيرلاند.
And finally, point number three:
وأخيراً، النقطة رقم ثلاثة:
Whatever one wants to say about Lesterland,
مهما كان أحد يريد أن يقول عن ليستيرلاند،
against the background of its history, its traditions,
على خلفية تاريخها و تقاليدها
in our land, in USA-land, Lesterland is a corruption,
في بلادنا، في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية، ليستيرلاند هي فساد،
a corruption.
فساد.
Now, by corruption I don't mean brown paper bag cash
الآن، أنا لا أقصد بالفساد الحقائب الورقية المملوءة بالمال
secreted among members of Congress.
التي يخفيها اعضاء الكونغرس.
I don't mean Rod Blagojevich sense of corruption.
أنا لا اقصد الفساد على طريقة رود بلاجوفيتش.
I don't mean any criminal act.
أنا لا أقصد أي عمل إجرامي.
The corruption I'm talking about is perfectly legal.
الفساد الذي أتحدث عنه قانوني تماما.
It's a corruption relative to the framers' baseline for this republic.
إنه فساد متجذر في أسس هذه الجمهورية.
The framers gave us what they called a republic,
المؤسسين تركوا لنا ما سموه جمهورية,
but by a republic they meant a representative democracy,
ولكن بجمهورية كانوا يقصدون ديمقراطية تمثيلية,
and by a representative democracy, they meant a government,
و بديمقراطية تمثيلية كانوا يقصدون حكومة,
as Madison put it in Federalist 52, that would have a branch
كما وضعه ماديسون في 52 الفيدرالية،
that would be dependent upon the people alone.
جهاز الحكومة سيكون معتمدا على الشعب فقط.
So here's the model of government.
إليكم إذن نموذج الحكومة.
They have the people and the government
يوجد الشعب و الحكومة
with this exclusive dependency,
تابعين لبعضهم البعض تماما,
but the problem here is that Congress has evolved a different dependence,
لكن المشكلة هنا، هي أن الكونغرس طور تبعية مختلفة,
no longer a dependence upon the people alone,
لم تعد تبعية للشعب فقط,
increasingly a dependence upon the funders.
بل ايضا، وبشكل متزايد، تبعية لفائدة الممولين.
Now this is a dependence too,
الآن، هذه تبعية أيضا,
but it's different and conflicting from a dependence upon the people alone
إلا أنها مختلفة ومتضاربة مع مبدئ التبعية للشعب لوحده
so long as the funders are not the people.
طالما أن الممولين ليسوا هم عامة الشعب .
This is a corruption.
وهذا فساد.
Now, there's good news and bad news about this corruption.
الآن، هناك أخبار جيدة وأخبار سيئة عن هذا الفساد.
One bit of good news is that it's bipartisan,
احد الاخبار الجيدة هو الثنائية الحزبية,
equal-opportunity corruption.
تكافئ الفرص في الفساد.
It blocks the left on a whole range of issues that we on the left really care about.
يعرقل اليسار بسبب مجموعة من القضايا التي تهمنا
It blocks the right too, as it makes
كما انه يعرقل اليمين ايضا، بجعله
principled arguments of the right increasingly impossible.
جاعلا إيجاد حلول منطقية امرا مستحيلا.
So the right wants smaller government.
إذا اليمين يريد حكومة أصغر.
When Al Gore was Vice President, his team had an idea
عندما كان آل غور نائب رئيس، كان فريقه طموح
for deregulating a significant portion of the telecommunications industry.
لتحرير جزء كبير من صناعة الاتصالات السلكية واللاسلكية من قوانين تنظيمية.
The chief policy man took this idea to Capitol Hill,
عرض رئيس السياسات الامر على الكونغرس,
and as he reported back to me,
و أبلغني
the response was, "Hell no!
أن الجواب كان هو : لا بحق الجحيم!``
If we deregulate these guys,
ان عفينا هؤلاء الاشخاص من تلك القوانين التنظيمية,
how are we going to raise money from them?"
كيف سنحصل على المال من عندهم مستقبلا ؟``
This is a system that's designed to save the status quo,
وهذا هو نظام الذي صُمم لإنقاذ الوضع الراهن،
including the status quo of big and invasive government.
بما في ذلك الوضع الحالي لحكومة ضخمة و جائحة.
It works against the left and the right,
أنه يعمل ضد اليسار واليمين،
and that, you might say, is good news.
و هذا، إن أردتم القول، هو الخبر الجيد.
But here's the bad news.
ولكن ها هي الأخبار السيئة.
It's a pathological, democracy-destroying corruption,
إنها قضية فساد مرضية، مدمرة للديمقراطية,
because in any system
لأنه في أي نظام
where the members are dependent upon
يتوقف اعضاءه على
the tiniest fraction of us for their election,
أصغر جزء منا في إنتخابهم,
that means the tiniest number of us,
وهذا يعني أصغر عدد منا،
the tiniest, tiniest number of us,
أصغر، أصغر منا،
can block reform.
يمكنه وقف الإصلاح.
I know that should have been, like, a rock or something.
اعلم أن صخرة أو شيء من هذا القبيل قد يكون اكثر صحة
I can only find cheese. I'm sorry. So there it is.
لكن لم أجد إلا الجبنة. أنا آسف. ها انتم ذا.
Block reform.
وقف الإصلاح.
Because there is an economy here, an economy of influence,
بما أنه يوجد اقتصاد هنا،اقتصاد تأثير،
an economy with lobbyists at the center
إقتصاد جماعات الضغط
which feeds on polarization.
الذين يتغدون على الإستقطاب;
It feeds on dysfunction.
فإن تواجد خلل وظيفي يغديها.
The worse that it is for us,
كلما إزداد سوء حالنا,
the better that it is for this fundraising.
كان ذلك أفضل لعملية جمع التبرعات.
Henry David Thoreau: "There are a thousand hacking
هنري ديفيد ثورو: "آلاف هي تحتاج التقطيع،
at the branches of evil to one who is striking at the root."
فروع الشر ضد فرد يضرب جذورها ``.
This is the root.
وهذا هو الجذر.
Okay, now, every single one of you knows this.
حسنا، الآن، كل واحد منكم يعرف هذا.
You couldn't be here if you didn't know this, yet you ignore it.
ما كنتم لتصبح هنا لو كيت تجهل هذه الامور، بالرغم من ذلك تتجاهلها.
You ignore it. This is an impossible problem.
تتجاهلونها.هذه مشكلة مستحيل حله.
You focus on the possible problems,
انتم تركزون على المشاكل الممكن حلها,
like eradicating polio from the world,
مثل استئصال شلل الأطفال من العالم،
or taking an image of every single street across the globe,
أو أخذ صورة كل شارع عبر أنحاء العالم،
or building the first real universal translator,
أو بناء المترجم العالمي الحقيقي الأول،
or building a fusion factory in your garage.
أو بناء مصنع لانصهار في المرأب الخاص بك.
These are the manageable problems, so you ignore —
هذه هي المشاكل التي يمكن التحكم فيها، لذلك يمكنك تجاهل —
(Laughter) (Applause) —
(ضحك) (تصفيق) –
so you ignore this corruption.
لذا يمكنك تجاهل هذا الفساد.
But we cannot ignore this corruption anymore.
ولكن لا يمكننا أن نتجاهل هذا الفساد بعد الآن.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
We need a government that works.
ونحن بحاجة إلى حكومة تعمل.
And not works for the left or the right,
ولا تعمل لليسار أو اليمين،
but works for the left and the right,
لكنها تعمل لليسار واليمين،
the citizens of the left and right,
المواطنين من اليسار واليمين،
because there is no sensible reform possible
لأنه لا يوجد أي إصلاح معقول و ممكن
until we end this corruption.
حتى نضع حدا لهذا الفساد.
So I want you to take hold, to grab the issue you care the most about.
فلينتزع كل واحد منا المشكل الذي يؤرقه اكثر,
Climate change is mine, but it might be financial reform
تغير المناخ هو لي، ولكن قد يكون الإصلاح المالي
or a simpler tax system or inequality.
أو أبسط من النظام الضريبي أو عدم المساواة.
Grab that issue, sit it down in front of you,
إختر قضيتك، و اجلسها أمامك,
look straight in its eyes, and tell it there is no Christmas this year.
انظر في عينيها مباشرة في عينيها و اخبرها لن أجد لك حلا هذه السنة.
There will never be a Christmas.
لن اجد لك حلا ابداً.
We will never get your issue solved
لن يوجد لها حلاًّ
until we fix this issue first.
حتى نجده للقضية الأولى.
So it's not that mine is the most important issue. It's not.
قضيتي ليست هي أهم قضية.إنها ليست كذلك.
Yours is the most important issue, but mine is the first issue,
قضيتك هي هي القضية الأهم، لكن قضيتي هي القضية الأولى,
the issue we have to solve before we get to fix
القضية التي يجب ان نجد لها حلاً قبل أن نجده
the issues you care about.
للقضايا التي تؤرقكم.
No sensible reform, and we cannot afford
لا إصلاح ملموس، و لا يمكننا قبول
a world, a future, with no sensible reform.
عالم، مستقبل خالٍ من الإصلاح
Okay. So how do we do it?
حسنا. فكيف نفعل ذلك؟
Turns out, the analytics here are easy, simple.
تبين، التحليلات هنا سهلة وبسيطة.
If the problem is members spending an extraordinary
إذا كانت المشكلة هي تمضية الاعضاء زمن غير عادي
amount of time fundraising from the tiniest slice of America,
في جمع الاموال من اقلية الامريكيين ,
the solution is to have them spend less time fundraising
فإن الحل هو جعلهم يمضون زمن اقل في جمع الاموال
but fundraise from a wider slice of Americans,
و جمع التبرعات من شريحة اعرض من الامركيين,
to spread it out,
ان ان نقوي,
to spread the funder influence so that we restore the idea
ان نقوي مدى تأثير المتبرعين حتى نستعيد فكرة
of dependence upon the people alone.
الاعتماد على الشعب وحده.
And to do this does not require a constitutional amendment,
و القيام بذلك لا يتطلب تعديلاً دستوريا،
changing the First Amendment.
او تعديل البند الاول من الدستور.
To do this would require a single statute,
القيام بذلك يتطلب قانون واحد،
a statute establishing what we think of
قانون يؤسس
as small dollar funded elections,
لانتخابات ممولة بدولار واحد,
a statute of citizen-funded campaigns,
قانون ينظم حملات ممولة من طرف المواطنين,
and there's any number of these proposals out there:
و يوجد عدد مهم من مشريع قوانين مماثلة:
Fair Elections Now Act,
منظمة`` من اجل انتخابات نزيهة`` (Fair Elections Now Act)
the American Anti-Corruption Act,
القانون الأمريكي لمكافحة الفساد (the American Anti-Corruption Act)،
an idea in my book that I call the Grant and Franklin Project
فكرة في كتاب لي أن اسميها `بمشروع غرانت و فرانكلن`
to give vouchers to people to fund elections,
لإعطاء قسائم للشعب لتمويل الانتخابات،
an idea of John Sarbanes called the Grassroots Democracy Act.
فكرة لساربانيس جون اسمها "قانون الديمقراطية الشعبية".
Each of these would fix this corruption
كل من هذه يمكنه القضاء على مشكلة الفساد
by spreading out the influence of funders to all of us.
عن طريق توزيع تأثير الممولين عنا جميعا.
The analytics are easy here.
التحليلات واضحة هنا.
It's the politics that's hard, indeed impossibly hard,
السياسة هي الصعبة، بل صعبة لدرجة الاستحالة,
because this reform would shrink K Street,
لان مثل هذا الاصلاح سيقلص من نفوذ مجوعات الضغط المتواجدين ب`شارع. ك`
and Capitol Hill, as Congressman Jim Cooper,
و الكونغرس, و عضو الكونغرس جيم كوبر,
a Democrat from Tennessee, put it,
من خلال كلام عضو الحزب الدمقراطي بتينيسي,
has become a farm league for K Street, a farm league for K Street.
الكونغرس اصبح في خدمة مجموعات الضغط `بشارع. ك`
Members and staffers and bureaucrats have
الأعضاء والعاملين والبيروقراطيين لديهم
an increasingly common business model in their head,
نفس نموذج الحياة في عقولهم,
a business model focused on their life after government,
نموذج حول طريقة حياتهم بعد الحكومة
their life as lobbyists.
حياة كجماعة ضغط.
Fifty percent of the Senate between 1998 and 2004
خمسين في المئة من مجلس الشيوخ بين عامي 1998 و 2004
left to become lobbyists, 42 percent of the House.
غدرو ليشكلوا جماعات ضغط، و 42 في المئة من مجلس النواب.
Those numbers have only gone up,
و هذه الارقام في ارتفاع مستمر,
and as United Republic calculated last April,
و طبقا لاحصائيات `يونايتد ريبوبليك`
the average increase in salary for those who they tracked
متوسط زيادة دَخل الذين تتبعوهم
was 1,452 percent.
هو 1,452 بالمائة.
So it's fair to ask, how is it possible for them to change this?
ولذلك فمن الإنصاف أن نسأل، هل بإمكانهم تغيير هذا؟
Now I get this skepticism.
الآن استوعب هذه الشكوك.
I get this cynicism. I get this sense of impossibility.
استوعب هذه السخرية. استوعب هذا الشعور بالاستحالة.
But I don't buy it.
ولكن أنا لا أقبل ذلك.
This is a solvable issue.
هذه مشكلة قابلة للحل.
If you think about the issues our parents tried to solve
إذا كنت تفكر في القضايا التي حاول آبائنا حلها
in the 20th century,
في القرن العشرين،
issues like racism, or sexism,
قضايا مثل العنصرية أو التمييز على أساس الجنس،
or the issue that we've been fighting in this century, homophobia,
او موضع قتال هذا القرن، الخوف من المثلية،
those are hard issues.
تلك قضايا صعبة.
You don't wake up one day no longer a racist.
لا يستيقظ المرء يوما ما معافا من العنصرية.
It takes generations to tear that intuition, that DNA,
يستغرق الامر اجيالا لاستئصال هذا المرض، من حمضنا النووي,
out of the soul of a people.
من روح الناس.
But this is a problem of just incentives, just incentives.
ولكن هذه مشكلة حوافز فقط، حوافز فقط.
Change the incentives, and the behavior changes,
تغيير الحوافز، والتغييرات في السلوك،
and the states that have adopted small dollar funded systems
و الولايات التي تبنت نظام حملات انتخابية بدولار واحد
have seen overnight a change in the practice.
قد شهدت تغييرا في الممارسة بين عشية وضحاها.
When Connecticut adopted this system,
عندما اعتمدت ولاية كونيتيكت هذا النظام،
in the very first year, 78 percent of elected representatives
في السنة الأولى، 78 في المئة من الممثلين المنتخبين
gave up large contributions and took small contributions only.
تخلوا عن التبرعات الضخمة و قبلوا بالتبرعات الصغيرة,
It's solvable,
c،
not by being a Democrat,
ليس عن طريق التصرف كدمقراطي,
not by being a Republican.
او التصرف كجمهوري,
It's solvable by being citizens, by being citizens,
أنها قابلة للحل بالتصرف كمواطنين، بالتصرف كمواطنين,
by being TEDizens.
بالتصرف كاعضاء `تيد`
Because if you want to kickstart reform,
لأنه إذا كنت تريد تحريك الإصلاح،
look, I could kickstart reform
انظر، يمكنني تحريك الاصلاح
at half the price of fixing energy policy,
بنصف سعر إصلاح سياسة الطاقة،
I could give you back a republic.
يمكنني ان استعيد لك جمهورية.
Okay. But even if you're not yet with me,
حسنا، اذا لم تساندوني بعد,
even if you believe this is impossible,
حتى إذا كنتم تعتقدون أن هذا أمر مستحيل،
what the five years since I spoke at TED has taught me
الدرس الذي تعلمته خمس سنوات بعد عرضي ب`تيد`
as I've spoken about this issue again and again is,
و مع تكرار حديثي عن هذه القضية مرة أخرى، ومرة أخرى،
even if you think it's impossible, that is irrelevant.
بالرغم من اعتقادكم ان الامر مستحيل, غير مهم
Irrelevant.
غير مهم.
I spoke at Dartmouth once, and a woman stood up after I spoke,
القيت عرضا بداترمونت يوما، فوقفت امرأة بعد عرضي
I write in my book, and she said to me,
ثم قالت,
"Professor, you've convinced me this is hopeless. Hopeless.
``بروفيسور لقد اقنعتني ان الامر ميؤوس منه,ميؤوس منه.
There's nothing we can do."
لا نستطيع ان نقوم بأي شئ.``
When she said that, I scrambled.
عندما قالت هذا، ارتبكت.
I tried to think, "How do I respond to that hopelessness?
حاولت التفكير `` كيف اجيب عن مثل هذا اليأس؟
What is that sense of hopelessness?"
ما هذا النوع من اليأس؟
And what hit me was an image of my six-year-old son.
فخطر ببالي ابني الصغير عمره 6 سنوات.
And I imagined a doctor coming to me and saying,
و تخيتلت طبيبا يخبرني
"Your son has terminal brain cancer, and there's nothing you can do.
ابنك في المرحلة الأخيرة من سرطان الدماغ، و لا يوجد شيئ يمكنك فعله.
Nothing you can do."
لا شيء يمكن فعله.``
So would I do nothing?
هل كنت لأقوم بشيء ما؟
Would I just sit there? Accept it? Okay, nothing I can do?
هل ساقف مكتوف الايدي؟ اتقبل الامر؟
I'm going off to build Google Glass.
هل سأذهب لإختراع ``نظارات جوجل``
Of course not. I would do everything I could,
طبعاً لا. كنت لأفعل كل شيئ استطيع.
and I would do everything I could because this is what love means,
كنت لأفعل كل شيئ استطيع لان هذا معنى الحب,
that the odds are irrelevant and that you do
ان تكون احتمالات النجاح معدومة، و رغم ذلك تفعل
whatever the hell you can, the odds be damned.
ما تستطيع بحق الجحيم, اللعنة على الاحتمالات.
And then I saw the obvious link, because even we liberals
عندئد لاحظت الرابط، لانه بالرغم من كوننا لبراليين
love this country.
نحن نحب هذه البلاد.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And so when the pundits and the politicians
عندما يقول النقاد و السياسيين
say that change is impossible,
ان التغيير مستحيل,
what this love of country says back is,
ردُّ حب هذه البلاد يكون
"That's just irrelevant."
``لا يهم``
We lose something dear,
سنخسر شيئا عزيزا,
something everyone in this room loves and cherishes,
شيئ كل فرد في هذه القاعة يحبه و يعتز به,
if we lose this republic, and so we act
إذا خسرنا هذه الجمهورية, لذ نعمل
with everything we can to prove these pundits wrong.
بكل جهدنا حتى نوضح للنقاد انهم مخطئين.
So here's my question:
لذا سؤالي هو كالتالي:
Do you have that love?
هل لديك ذلك الحب؟
Because if you do,
لانه إن كان لديك,
then what the hell are you, what are the hell are we doing?
إذا ماذا بحق الجحيم أنت، ماذا نحن بحق الجحيم نفعل؟
When Ben Franklin was carried from the constitutional convention
بعد انتهاء بين فراكلين من المؤتمر الدستوري
in September of 1787, he was stopped in the street by a woman who said,
في سبتمبر 1787، اوقف في الشرع من طرف امرأة, سألته.
"Mr. Franklin, what have you wrought?"
``السيد فراكلين، ما الذي كتبتم؟``
Franklin said, "A republic, madam, if you can keep it."
فراكلين اجاب، `` جمهورية، يا سيدتي، ان استطعتم الحفاظ عليها``
A republic. A representative democracy.
جمهورية.ديمقراطية تمثيلية.
A government dependent upon the people alone.
حكومة تعتمد على الشعب لوحده.
We have lost that republic.
لقد خسرنا تلك الجمهورية.
All of us have to act to get it back.
كلنا يجيب ان نعمل لنستعيدها.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا لكم. شكرا لكم. شكرا لكم. (تصفيق)